Douglas Goldstein, CFPÂ®, Financial Planner & Investment Advisor
Even informed citizens sometimes have a hard time getting through the fog of political
rhetoric to decide if government policies are good or bad. They can get a lot of help
from the writing of today's guest. He investigates the facts and examines similar policies, and
then he applies common sense and logic. Dr. Thomas Sowell is the author of more than 30
books, and we're going to talk today about his most recent book called Dismantling America,
which is a collection of columns that showcase his views on political, cultural, economic,
and legal issues. Welcome, Dr. Sowell, and tell us what is the meaning of the title of
your newest book.
I think that the current administration is doing more than simply passing policies that
are very questionable in themselves. What they're doing is changing the whole procedure
by which the American government operates, and I think that's going to do long-run damage
even if the policies themselves get repealed. For example, this practice of passing enormously
large and far-reaching bills without any opportunity for the public to know what's
in them or, in some cases, for even most members of Congress to know what's in them. Things
like the waivers, for example, they can give to certain companies from the provisions of
the new health care law. Well, the ability to give waivers is the ability to withhold
waivers and, therefore, to punish people who dare to speak out. One insurance company
recently said that they were going to have to raise premiums because of the Obamacare
legislation. Well, they were immediately told by one of the Cabinet members that there will
be zero tolerance for what the administration calls misinformation, which is to say that
this insurance company can look for federal retaliation for having spoken the truth.
Well, isn't socialism not just spreading the wealth around? It's being able to spread
the wealth to your pals and make sure your friends get the goodies.
Oh, absolutely. I mean, the administration, they're great at rhetoric. That's their strong
suit. And so they say they're against special interests, but that just means that their
special interests aren't called special interests.
Well, what do you think about Obama appointing all these czars who never had Senate confirmation?
Again, it's circumventing the Constitution and it's circumventing the public, because
the Constitution is the vehicle that allows the public to determine what kind of laws
they want to live under. And so if you can appoint people and call them czars instead
of Cabinet members, even though they may wield powers greater than the Cabinet members, if
you can do that, you've circumvented the Constitution. And then the Constitution can't
protect us unless we first protect the Constitution, that is, unless we vote against people who
circumvent the Constitution, even if the particular policy that they vote for may not be particularly
objectionable in themselves.
Well, why is anybody surprised Obama said that he wanted to fundamentally transform
the United States of America?
Well, I think no one believed that he meant what he was actually going to do. They may
have thought this was just some political rhetoric, but everything in the man's past
suggests that he is fundamentally opposed to the values and the procedures and the governing
principle to this country. And so now they're shocked to discover that he is what he's always
been, but wish they didn't bother to find out before voting.
We're talking today with Dr. Thomas Sowell about his new book, Dismantling America. And
he has, Obama has given us so many bad decisions. What's your comment about bailing out the
people who bought houses that they couldn't afford?
It's unbelievable. What is unbelievable is not that the government would do that, because
the government would do so many questionable things just for short-run political advantage.
What is incredible is there's so little criticism of it. When the obvious objection is, why
should I, who never owned a house until I was 50 years old, and have never owned a house
that is as costly as some of these that we're bailing out, why should I have to pay for
these people who went ahead and bought a house that they couldn't afford?
That's right. That really annoys me as much as anything. My mother and father never owned
a house, and the idea that you'd be a better citizen if somebody induced you to buy a house
that you really couldn't afford is just an offensive idea.
That notion that housing determines behavior goes back well over a hundred years, and it
is defied over a hundred years of evidence to the contrary. It's certainly true that
if you find a neighborhood with nice houses, chances are it will have a lower crime rate,
it will have better schools, and so forth. But this is the post-hoc fallacy. People of
a certain kind have certain kinds of houses, and they have certain kinds of educational
values.
We're talking today with Dr. Thomas Sowell, and you mention in the book that when you
were in your 20s, you were a little bit fascinated by the Marxist philosophy. What persuaded
you that private enterprise was better than the government running the economy?
Working for the government. You know, I was still a Marxist after I had taken a course
from Milton Friedman, but within three months of going to work for the government, I began
to change, because I realized that I was in the Labor Department, that government agencies
have their own priorities, and to expect them to carry out policies that benefit others,
when in fact their main purpose is to benefit themselves, is just very unrealistic.
What about the whole idea that if government runs it, such as healthcare, it's going to
cost less?
I don't know what the government runs that has ever cost less.
You think government coming into it is a major reason for the extraordinary rise in
tuition? You're on a college campus, and you...
Oh yes, my goodness. There have been studies that show for every dollar of government aid
to education, tuition rises by 50 cents. So when you start increasing government aid,
it's like a dog chasing its tail. I mean, he doesn't get any closer, no matter how fast
he runs.
Well, they've unfortunately sold a lot of people on this idea that the government running
healthcare is going to save us all money, as well as give us better health, and now
Obama's put a czar in front, who thinks the British system is really great.
Oh my goodness, I'm staggered, and I'm very disappointed in American media, because there's
so much in the British media about what is wrong with their medical system. I mean, the
women, for example, who have had their babies in British hospitals, not in the operating
room, but in elevators, and in the hallways, and so forth, because they get neglected to
the point where the baby's coming, and there's nobody there to take care of them.
Well, I think the American people have caught on to what's wrong with Obamacare, because
I think Obama thought we were all going to like it after the law was passed, but it now
appears that the majority of the American people really do want to repeal it.
Well, I would even question whether he believed that, or whether he simply said that, because
if you really believe the people are going to like this after the law was passed, you
would have it go into effect certainly before the 2012 presidential election, and perhaps
before the 2010 congressional election. But in fact, the law was written to go into effect
after the 2012 election. So it's clearly, he felt that this was something that he wanted
to put in there, and whether the people like it or not, there won't be much they can do
about it if they'd only learn about it after he's been re-elected.
Thomas Sowell, our special guest, here on Ego Forum Live. Phyllis Schlafly is with you
24-7, of course, at EgoForum.org, and more of this conversation continues next.
Eagle Forum Education Center in St. Louis is the headquarters of Eagle Forum's many educational activities.
The center houses a large library of 20th century American history, a unique collection of DVDs and CDs, and extraordinary archives.
Eagle Forum's publications include Education Reporter, bringing you important news about parents' rights and public school curriculum.
Eagle Forum sponsors activities especially for college students and for Teen Eagles,
including an annual Collegians Leadership Summit held each summer in Washington, D.C.
Eagle Forum sponsors two radio series.
Phyllis Schlafly's three-minute commentaries heard daily on 550 stations, and this Saturday live call-in program now heard on 75 stations.
Both broadcasts are streamed on the Internet at eagleforum.org.
Eagle Forum, a conservative organization of dedicated Americans, invites you to visit our website at eagleforum.org.
You've probably heard that all public schools are mandated to give reading tests, and many parents are worrying whether their children will pass.
If you want to find out if your child's reading skills are all they should be, we invite you to give Eagle Forum's first reading test in the privacy of your own home.
Any child who has finished first grade should be able to pass this test.
It will enable you to find out if your child can really read or if he has been taught to memorize a few dozen frequently used words
and then just guess at other words from the pictures on the page.
Eagle Forum's simple test will tell you whether your child is really reading.
Don't let your child fall behind in school because he is a poor reader.
Call 1-800-700-5228 and ask for our free reading test.
That's 1-800-700-5228.
And you can see Eagle Forum's first reading test on the website TurboReader.com.
Look up the website www.turboreader.com.
Just about every week, Phyllis Schlafly takes questions and comments, but this week, Phyllis is going the full hour with her special guest, Tarma Sol.
Eagle Forum Live continues. Here again, Phyllis Schlafly.
We're talking today with Dr. Tarma Sol of the Hoover Institution in California,
and I want to switch the subject a little bit to education.
I know you write on that in many of your books, and the misuse of words.
For example, now they're trying to tell us that national standards are the way to go,
and, of course, the word social justice has become very trendy in the schools.
Tell us what that really means.
I must confess at the outset that it's totally beyond my ability to tell you what that phrase means
because I have read books going back 100 years, and nobody has ever defined it.
I guess what they have in mind is that all sorts of groups ought to be equally represented in all sorts of places,
which is particularly amazing to me after having spent decades studying ethnic and other groups around the world.
Nowhere on this planet do I find groups that are the same.
If black and white Americans, for example, were the same, they would be the only two groups on this planet that are the same.
I mean, the Northern Italians and Southern Italians aren't the same.
The Scottish Lowlanders and the Scottish Highlanders aren't the same.
People in North Korea are not the same as people in South Korea.
I mean, you can go through everywhere you go that there are different groups.
You find incredible differences.
You find differences in alcoholism rates, infant mortality rates.
You name it, there are differences.
And yet, so many of our policies and even our court decisions are based on the notion that if all the groups aren't the same in some respect,
somebody else must be to blame.
And, well, I think social justice in many cases has come to mean teaching the kids that they live in an unjust, oppressive, racist society.
Yes, yes.
And, therefore, they must organize under some community organizer and take power and wealth away from people who have it.
Oh, absolutely, absolutely.
You know, it's funny, Dr. Sowell, not only have some of these words become bad,
but it's funny the way the White House recognizes that the word stimulus has become a negative word
because people don't believe the stimulus spending did stimulate any jobs, at least in private industry.
Well, I think that most of the evidence would justify substituting the word sedative for stimulus.
I've done some research on this, and you can trace the banks on which the government dumped great sums of money
and discover that the following year they made substantially fewer loans than they made the previous year.
And, similarly, in other areas where they've dumped all this money and the money just sits there.
I mean, right now, both the banks and private industry, as well as individuals, have more money sitting idle than they have had in decades.
Well, I think the money that did get spent got spent to create more government jobs.
Oh, absolutely.
Not private enterprise jobs.
No, and the great problem is that the various policies of the administration are making it more difficult to create private industry jobs.
And the government jobs that they create, obviously the government doesn't create any wealth,
so they take the wealth out of the private economy, use it to create the government jobs.
But, of course, that means the private economy has less money to create jobs than they had before.
And so there's no net increase in jobs.
I wish, Dr. Sowell, you'd talk a little bit about your views about immigration
and how we used to assimilate the immigrants into our society, but they're not doing that now.
And we hope that we would be a great country.
I saw Marco Rubio saying on television that his father was a bartender and his wife was a waitress.
His mother was a waitress.
And it was such a great country.
Now he's running for the Senate.
And America's such a great country where this can happen.
He pointed out how that absolutely could not happen in the Cuba that he came from.
Oh, absolutely.
And Obama doesn't believe we're an exceptional, unique country.
Not at all.
And heaven knows he should have more reason than most people to be glad he was born here.
You're right about the immigrants.
I mean, people point out how all these millions of European immigrants were integrated into society and so on.
It's true.
But it's also true that most of these groups did so by making great efforts,
sometimes individual and sometimes organized efforts, to assimilate to the American society.
Today, not only is that not happening in the organizational sense,
the organizations that exist to represent different groups, such as La Raza, for example,
are doing their best to keep the foreigners foreign.
And these activists have such gall that they have even opposed letting the parents of children,
that is, the Hispanic parents of Hispanic children, decide whether they want the kids taught in English or Spanish
because they know the parents want their children taught in English.
Because that's how they'll get ahead.
I remember, actually it was during the Bush administration,
I tried to get Congress to say that the use of the bilingual education money coming from the federal government would be parents' option.
Well, everybody was against that.
They didn't want parents to have the option.
That's right.
Well, you know, this is part of the general arrogance that extends far beyond this issue.
They want to be able to decide what is right and, to the extent possible, cut the ordinary people out of the loop.
I mean, that's why these bills were passed in such a hurry.
Even when they're bills, they won't take place until years later.
So it's not like they're hurrying to get the thing in operation.
It's like they're hurrying to get it passed before the rest of us can find out.
And that really permeates everything that they say and do.
Well, Nancy Pelosi was even pretty frank about that.
She said, we have to pass the bill and then you'll find out what's in it.
That's right.
And that is the attitude.
So many people think of the left as being for the common man.
I've been on the left.
I've studied the left.
The left is for the left making the decisions and having those decisions handed down to the rest of us
where we can like it or love it.
One of the things that I find really disturbing about President Obama is the way he wants to bow to world opinion
and apologize for us around the world.
I know you've had a number of columns on that covered in your book, Dismantling America, which is a wonderful new book.
Comment on that.
We want to maintain our individual identity as the land of freedom and prosperity.
Absolutely.
But again, this is a man who I don't believe has any faith in America as it is
and who thinks our only redeeming feature is that we can elect people like him to change us to what he thinks we ought to be.
And I think this is part of that.
Dinesh D'Souza has argued that he really has a sort of third-world mentality of envy and
resentment of the United States, and my feeling is very much the same, that this is not a
man who loves this country, this is not a man who's dedicated to his values.
And it's incredible to me that the American people could have elected such a man to the
high office he has, which means he holds really our lives in his hands, not only without knowing
what he was like from his track record, but disregarding what they do know about his past,
in order to invest him with what they imagine to be his good qualities.
Well, he led a privileged life in our country, he never had a real job.
Yeah.
He talked about all these shovel-ready jobs, he never handled any shovels.
You know, this goes beyond Obama, but one of the things that has amazed me is that people
who were born in very humble circumstances have so often been so dedicated to this country,
and people who are given all sorts of privileges, including millionaires, have turned against
this.
You know, right after 9-11, when all these American flags were flying in various neighborhoods
and homes and other places, I went out to the University of California at Berkeley,
and on that entire campus I did not see one American flag flying.
The first American flag that I saw was on my way back from Berkeley, when I was passing
through a low-income black neighborhood in Oakland.
That's where I first saw an American flag flying.
What do you think would happen if we actually enforced our laws against illegal immigration?
Would our crops rot in the field?
We won't be able to eat strawberries anymore, and the chicken plants will go out of business?
Do you know, what gets me is that we have had chronic agricultural surpluses that cost
the taxpayers billions of dollars every year.
And so even if agricultural output went down, there isn't a slight danger that we'd be without
strawberries or anything else.
Well, I think the two political parties do cooperate in winking their eyes at this illegal
immigration.
You know, they've now admitted that the fence, the virtual fence, was a billion-dollar mistake.
It won't work at all.
Well, I don't think it was a mistake from their standpoint.
It got the political pressure off them, and it was worth it to spend a billion dollars
worth of the taxpayers' money for that.
I'm not at all convinced that they ever thought at the outset that this thing was going to
work.
Well, one of our congressmen, the one from Iowa, Steve King, who was in the construction
business before he had a real job, before he went to Congress, I saw him on C-SPAN showing
how he would build a fence, and how he would pour the concrete, and how he'd put the blocks
in.
And he had a model, and it looked pretty simple.
We could hire some of those people to build the fence.
You know, it's not like building a fence is not some unprecedented problem.
It's not rocket science?
No.
I mean, you know, I've seen the Berlin Wall, I saw the fence between China and Hong Kong
before Hong Kong became part of China.
You just don't get over those kinds of fences, because they're serious about stopping you.
Now, if you're going to have a fence where you can easily run up the side of the fence
and bolt right on over, well, of course it's not going to be very effective.
But that doesn't mean there are no effective fences.
If there were no effective fences, the entire population of Eastern Europe would probably
have moved to Western Europe during the year of the Soviet Union.
Good point.
Today, Phyllis Schlafly and her special guest Thomas Sowell are prerecorded.
Next week, of course, Ego Forum Live returns to its regular format, where we take questions
and comments from around the country.
In the meantime, visit Phyllis online anytime at egoforum.org.
The Phyllis Schlafly Report is a unique newsletter that is in its 42nd year of monthly publication.
Phyllis Schlafly writes about topics that are so important to you, your family, and
your family's future.
You can request a sample report at any time.
Recent issues on education include how to train our leaders to be conservative, the
radical resolutions passed by the National Education Association, and liberal plans to
subvert the U.S. Constitution.
Other reports cover such vital topics as what's happening on college campuses, how the public
schools are turning out liberals, the rising costs of tolerating illegal aliens, and Congress
must curb activist judges.
The Phyllis Schlafly Report is the best bargain in print.
It's full of useful information you can use to write your congressman and educate your
friends.
Get a free sample by calling 1-800-736-3202.
That's 1-800-736-3202.
Or online, go to egoforum.org.
Are you concerned about border security or about the effect that millions of illegal
aliens are having on illegal drugs, crime, disease, and health care costs?
These are only some of the many subjects of national importance covered in the Phyllis
Schlafly Report, a monthly newsletter Phyllis has been writing for 42 years.
The Phyllis Schlafly Report covers a lot of other subjects too, such as education, both
public school and college, court cases, family and feminism, health care, and United Nations
treaties.
The Phyllis Schlafly Report always gives you more facts and fewer words than anything
in print.
This newsletter is also useful to carry with you to share with your friends.
You can get a free copy of the Phyllis Schlafly Report on a subject of your particular interest
by calling EgoForum at 1-800-736-3202.
Or you can log on to EgoForum's website at egoforum.org.
Today, Phyllis Schlafly and her special guest Thomas Sowell are prerecorded.
Next week, of course, EgoForum Live returns to its regular format where we take questions
and comments from around the country.
In the meantime, visit Phyllis online anytime at egoforum.org.
Now, once again, Phyllis Schlafly.
We're talking today with Dr. Thomas Sowell, and I know that you know what's going on with
the universities.
Do you see a change in the student body now from what it was when you started out teaching
in colleges?
Well, I haven't actually taught in about the last 30 years, but I think that's not...
But I obviously did see some changes, because I really...
I started my academic career to be a teacher, not to be a writer and researcher.
But I saw enough changes between the time I first started in 1962 and in 1980, when
I taught my last class, that I realized that this was just no longer where I wanted to
be.
Well, they haven't read much of anything.
They don't know much history.
Oh, my gosh, no.
You can't presuppose anything in teaching, because, well, at least of all history, there
are all sorts of places.
I mean, we're talking prestigious places where you can graduate without a clue about the
history of this country.
Yes, I understand there's one California university where you can fulfill the history requirement
by taking a course in the history of rock and roll.
Yes.
Well, there are all kinds of these sort of boutique courses in highly specialized things,
and they're very easy for the professors to teach, because the professor does a doctoral
dissertation on the history of winemaking in France.
Well, he has a ton of material.
It's far easier for him to teach a course on the history of winemaking in France than
to teach a course on the history of Europe or on the history of the United States.
Dr. Sowell, we've been talking about the great variety of subjects you deal with in your
latest book, Dismantling America, but I have to tell you, my favorite one of your books
is your one about intellectuals, and I have to ask you to give some of your choice remarks
of what you think about intellectuals and their influence on our society.
Well, the influence is the easiest to summarize.
I think it has been largely negative.
They have been part of this process which really set the stage for the dismantling of
America.
They've been enormously critical of everything that has happened in this country.
They've taken the sins of the human race, which are common around the world, and they've
talked about them as if they're the peculiarities of our society, of virtually everything bad
that has gone on in the history of this country has gone on to a worse extent.
both other countries around the world
uh... and yet you never look you never learn any of that
uh... my gosh uh... one one of the thing they love to talk about a slavery
united states
well and well i said let's say talk about all the time
you would think
that the only people who were ever in slave were blocked when played by white
in the united states or at most
in european society
uh... neither i think most of the slaves in the history of the world would be the
black-and-white
they were the people who were conquered in war weren't they
they were they were people who were who were uh... abducted by pirates
uh... there was slavery every everywhere you found human being
you found slavery
uh... i mean
there was a time not that many centuries ago when people could not
conceive of a world without slavery
i mean that the the uh... christian monasteries in europe
the buddhist monasteries in asia had slaves
uh... even in the uh... ideal society in the novel utopia
utopia had slaves they couldn't even conceive of
of even an ideal society without slaves
uh... what was peculiar about the united states about western civilization
was that this was the first and for a long time the only civilization
that turned against it
and destroyed it
but that we never hear
well this thing about uh... crying about uh... past uh...
past sins
uh... you know i uh... spent
ten years of my life fighting the equal rights amendment and i can tell you how
many times i was in a debate
uh... before uh... legislative hearing or elsewhere
and my opponent is still crying about the time when women didn't have the
right to vote in this country
now at my advanced age i don't even know anybody who can remember that time
but they're still whining about it
oh yeah and the other thing too is that
a great injustice to your ancestors is not necessarily a great injustice to you
uh... if you look at the history of western europe and western europe became
illiterate
because the romans conquered it now nobody considered the romans
sweethearts
i mean they slaughtered people by the thousands they oppressed the people they
conquered
and so forth
but the net result
well for today's western europeans
is that their society has got a huge advantage over eastern europe
because their languages for example
uh... had roman letters
centuries before the languages of eastern europe
uh... had letters
and and and and and you see that reflected to this day
i think quite similarly here in the united states
uh... there's no question that people who were
brought in bondage to africa from africa here to be mistreated and so forth
they suffered a lot
but of course the reason the black population of the united states is the most
prosperous black population in the world
was because of the injustices done to our ancestors
uh... we're talking today with doctor thomas seoul
uh... let me ask you this question
all the polls show that self-identified conservatives
outnumber liberals
self-identified liberals about two to one
uh... but yet we've elected the most left-wing president in history that
doesn't make sense how did that happen
i think uh... and and and and and and a few words
the ineptness of the republican party
i mean it's like it's like it's like when you're dealt the high cards in the
game
and your opponent wins it
well that's that's that's the way it is well we we uh...
we hope that the elections are going to change that because
uh... the remedies i think the remedies for our problems are there in the
constitution
absolutely
and uh... that's uh... apparently the liberals are very much annoyed when
tea-partiers
uh... hold up copies of the constitution and say we have to get back to the
constitution but that's really what we do need to do
absolutely because that's really what enables us
to be a self-governing country
and freedom
again back to uh... foreign policy
uh... you seem very concerned about iran getting nuclear bombs
what about that
i can't understand why other people aren't
i mean after nine eleven what we understand what the terrorists alike
uh... to think of those same people who did nine eleven as having nuclear
weapons
all of them that show
uh... through the through uh... through every american
and the other thing is we it's not like a soviet having nuclear weapons
because the soviet whatever their fault were not suicidal
and they knew that they bomb new york we would wipe moscow off the face of the
earth
the people in iran don't care about people who run iran the people who live
back here
the people who are who have dictatorial power in iran often addicts
and if they if they if they can wipe out uh...
new york in chicago in los angeles and we we wipe out their on
their they've got their come out ahead of the game as far as they're concerned
well they teach that suicide is great that you can have them
but that's right so i mean you can't you cannot just
deter suicide bombers
and and so suicide bombers with nuclear weapons are just the most frightening
thing in the world
do you think that uh...
uh... what obama's doing is taking us into uh... european-style socialism
and why is that so awful
well among that will provide all of the year to go to all things are wrong with
european-style socialist but they don't have
they've they typically have higher unemployment rates than we do
unemployment that last longer than we do
their medical systems run by government are far far inferior to ours
and so on
uh... but i think the thing that really is the point of no return is a nuclear
iran
because uh...
it took only two bombs for japan to surrender after at the end of world war
two
i think the japanese were a lot tougher than than we are now
i do not see this country doing anything other than surrendering
i mean it may be
inconceivable to most people
that the united states would ever surrender
but it was inconceivable that japan would surrender it had never surrendered
in this whole history
and yet just those two bombs did it
iraq the fact that we may have
you know a hundred bomb
or hundred times as many bombs as iran
means absolutely nothing if they're willing to die and we're not
uh... you do uh... make an interesting note that liberals are generally more
articulate in putting forth their policies and conservatives
so they come up with all these uh... smart phrases that sound good
do you have any advice for conservatives who want to do a better job of
communicating other than passing around your books of course
i think
uh... one of these you first have to have to
know that
being articulate
uh... is important in politics
uh... i i'm i'm appalled at how little uh... effort and thought republicans
seem to put into what they what they
say during election campaign
i would move up all uh... you know i think of bob dole
having forty five minutes on the air and just
further getaway
not addressing any of the problem
uh...
that you you can't do something unless you know what it is you want to do
and i think that's one of the things ought to be the top of the list but i
think those find that they're improving
thomas all our special guest here on eagle forum live phyllis schlafly is
with you twenty four seven of course it ego forum dot org
and more of this conversation continues
and
the biggest scandal in education today is allowing children to be promoted from
grade to grade and even graduate from high school
without ever learning how to read
school should teach kids how to read in the first grade by a real phonics method
parents can be easily fooled because first graders are able to memorize a few
dozen one-syllable words
and then the books use those same words over and over again
how can you tell if your child is really reading or if he's just reciting a few
words he's memorized and guessing at others
phyllis schlafly has developed a simple reading test you can use at home to find
out whether your child can actually read or is just guessing at the words
make sure your son or daughter has every chance to succeed don't leave it up to
the schools to teach your child this vital skill
order your free reading test by calling one eight hundred seven hundred five two
two eight that's one eight hundred seven hundred five two two eight or see this
test online at turbo reader dot com
are you worried about the future of america and the kind of country your
children will be living in
do you think that one person cannot make a difference so why bother to write your
representatives if you think that you need to join eagle forum a national
organization of conservative and pro-family men and women who have learned
how to participate and be effective in the process of self-government and
public policy making
eagle forums achievements prove that citizen volunteers can affect government
policies in congress state legislatures city councils and school boards our
members have been successful in electing candidates at every level and in
persuading them to vote for good policies after they are elected it's
obvious there's much more to do and that's why we need your help you can get
a free sample of our materials by writing eagle forum alton illinois six
two oh oh two that's eagle forum alton illinois six two oh oh two or by going
to our website eagle forum dot org that's eagle forum dot o r g
Welcome back to Ego Forum Live, this is Phyllis Schlafly and we're continuing with the great
economist Thomas Sowell explaining why Republicans are often very inarticulate in explaining
what they want to do.
I remember back during the 1994 government shutdown when the plain fact was that the
Republican Congress had voted more money than the government had had before, and so there
was no shortage of money to run the government.
And yet when Clinton began pushing the idea that Republicans caused the government to
shut down by not giving them enough money, the Republicans came on the air and they started
talking about OMB statistics versus CBO statistics.
Well, good heavens, man, you need to come on the air and say, no, we gave them the money.
He chose not to do it and he's lying.
I mean, people can understand that.
But if you want to go all around Washington and speak, you can't expect the public to
understand what you're talking about.
Well, I remember meeting with the Republican leadership at that time and and I said, well,
what is your plan B if Clinton doesn't do what you expect?
And they didn't have any plan B.
I want to ask you another question.
We want more transparency, as Obama said, but we some people have urged that all
congressional hearings and court proceedings and arguments be televised.
But you don't think that's a helpful idea, right?
No, if I if I if I had my way, I would cut out the C-SPAN coverage of of Congress.
These these are these are staged events.
These these are not sort of candid camera kinds of looks at how Congress is working.
The Congress, the people in Congress know that the cameras on and they behave and say
things in front of the camera that have nothing to do with what they're going to do when
they make their backroom deal.
And so this is a charade for the sake of the public.
Well, and I don't think people would get much out of the arguments before the courts
either. I kind of agree with you on that, especially there, because unless you know
the legal framework, you have no idea.
I mean, especially in appellate court, I mean, maybe a trial court, you could figure
out who's guilty and who's innocent.
But an appellate court is not not not taking that, not making that decision.
They're deciding whether the rules of the game were played when this trial was held.
And unless you happen to know what the procedure should have been, you have no way of
knowing whether what was done was good, bad or indifferent.
Well, you talk about need need some clever words to describe some of these people who
are destroying our heritage.
My word for the judges is supremacist because they really think they really do think
they're supreme over the other branches of government and and the people.
What about that?
But tragically, they are so long as nobody objects.
I mean, would you would you agree with me that that the founding fathers plan for the
judiciary to be the least powerful branch of government, but the judges have made it
the most powerful because they're deciding all these major issues?
Oh, absolutely.
Oh, there's a judge who decided that firefighters can't be promoted in New York
because they don't have the right demographic mix of people who pass the test.
Now, no one gave him that power, but unless someone challenges it, you know, people like
that are not going to stop unless they get stopped.
And yet the idea has gotten out there to be against judges is to be against the rule of
law. Well, the rule of law was never meant to be simply the rule of judges.
You have another interesting book called Economic Facts and Fallacies.
What are these a couple of these fallacies that people have fallen for?
Oh, my heavens.
There there there is the notion that.
Oh, I guess tax cuts for the rich are one of those that when the when the taxes are
cut, the benefits benefits go simply to the rich.
And of course, there's a lot of confusion between tax rates and tax revenues.
Tax rates can go down and tax while tax revenues go up.
And in fact, many of the tax rate cuts beginning in the 1920s and during the Kennedy
administration, Reagan and Bush administrations have, in fact, brought in more
revenue to the federal government because people no longer keep their money in tax
shelters. They invested in the economy and that then caused the economy to grow and the
government to make more taxes to collect more tax revenues, even though the rate of
taxation has been lowered.
But you never hear that.
You hear that as tax cuts for the rich.
Well, back to your one of your favorite subjects, the what's the matter with the
intellectuals isn't one of the additional things that matter with them is that there's
no there's no punishment in the in the whole system when they make wrong decisions
and encourage bad policies.
Oh, absolutely.
You can advocate policies, as was done in France in the 30s, that end up undermining
the nation's national defense so that France, which had fought for four long years
against the German invaders during the First World War, collapsed after six weeks of
fighting in the Second World War.
But but there's no intellectual who could be punished for that.
That was just one of the things that happened.
And certainly academics can't be punished if they turn out people from from the
universities who graduate not understanding of the history of the country, the nature
of constitutional government or any of the other things that they need in order to be
decent citizens.
Well, if you build a fence and it falls down, I guess you can be sued for faulty work.
Yeah, but it's virtually impossible to sue an intellectual for faulty work.
You can't even fire a faculty member who advocates policies that produce financial
ruin for the college.
You, of course, are an economist.
What do you think about Nixon saying we're all Keynesians now?
And I understand that the the British now have specifically rejected Keynesianism.
Oh, heavens. I think a lot of people have rejected it.
When when Obama was president elect, he was saying that we all know that we have to
spend more and concord with Keynesian theories.
A group of a large number of economists, in fact, took out full page ads, many of them by
economists with Nobel Prizes in economics saying, no, we don't have to do that.
But no, unfortunately, Richard Nixon would say almost anything if it was politically
expedient. One question we hadn't gotten around to is what do you think about the
danger of the Muslims today?
Very great danger and what is more dangerous.
Is that we dare not speak it as that one Williams discovered recently on NPR, but in
many of the countries of Europe, merely to warn about the dangers from the extremists
among the Muslims is to court being prosecuted under hate speech laws.
I mean, I think that that sort of thing will undoubtedly come to this country if Obama
gets a second term.
Well, whatever happened to all this diversity, people were one of the other
fraudulent words.
Diversity on a college campus means black leftist, white leftist, female leftist and
Hispanic leftist.
I mean, that's diversity, but diversity of ideas.
And after all, the university exists for ideas, not not for demographic representation,
but but diversity of ideas is virtually unknown at most of the college and university
campus in the country.
You have so many important books, which one would you recommend for the general public?
You do have a very big you have a book that has basic in the title.
It's basic economic economics.
Yes, it's it's it's the one that has sold the most copies here and has been translated
into the most languages overseas.
And it gives people a basic understanding of what economics are all about.
Yes, without without graphs, without equations and without jargon.
How about without math?
How about math?
No math, no math.
So there's one there's one arithmetic example.
But if you if you can master addition and subtraction, you're home free.
We've certainly had an interesting conversation with Dr.
Thomas Sowell of the Hoover Institution.
He's written many books.
I recommend them all.
His latest book is called Dismantling America.
It's a lot of his common sense logic to explain what's going on in language that the
average voter can understand.
I recommend it highly.
Also, his other books, the one on intellectuals and society and the one on basic
economics. Thank you so much, Dr.
Sowell, for being with us today.
We appreciate your time.
Keep up the good work.
Keep writing.
Thank you very much for having me.
Of course, you can join Phyllis anytime, 24-7 on EgoForum.org.
All the radio programs, they're archived on EgoForum.org.
So be sure to join us there.
And of course, Phyllis has some more thoughts next, right here on Ego Forum Live.
ğµ Music ğµ
Eagle Forum Education Center in St. Louis is the headquarters of Eagle Forum's many educational activities.
The center houses a large library of 20th century American history, a unique collection of DVDs and CDs, and extraordinary archives.
Eagle Forum's publications include Education Reporter, bringing you important news about parents' rights and public school curriculum.
Eagle Forum sponsors activities especially for college students and for Teen Eagles, including an annual Collegians Leadership Summit held each summer in Washington, D.C.
Eagle Forum sponsors two radio series, Phyllis Schlafly's 3-Minute Commentaries, heard daily on 550 stations, and this Saturday Live call-in program, now heard on 75 stations.
Both broadcasts are streamed on the Internet at EagleForum.org.
Eagle Forum, a conservative organization of dedicated Americans, invites you to visit our website at EagleForum.org.
I want to thank Dr. Thomas Sowell for joining us today on Eagle Forum Live.
He is one of the country's great scholars, a national treasure, and a reliable guide to help us separate rhetoric from reality.
His ability is absolutely critical at this juncture in our national history.
I highly recommend all of his books, as well as his syndicated column.
If everyone would read a couple of his books, a lot fewer people would be misled by smooth-talking politicians.
You can find a link to his latest book, Dismantling America, at the Eagle Forum website.
That's EagleForum.org. Be sure to join Phyllis next week.
And Phyllis, next week, did you know that one of the Pilgrim ships that was captured by Muslim pirates was sold into slavery in Morocco?
A historian will share some stories of the past that still affect us today, right here on Eagle Forum Live.